<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Category Theory | The Light Cone]]></title>
  <link href="http://rebcabin.github.com/blog/categories/category-theory/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://rebcabin.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-03-17T10:35:13-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://rebcabin.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Brian Beckman (rebcabin = brianbec)]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Category Theory Reveals Value of Autoiconicity]]></title>
    <link href="http://rebcabin.github.com/blog/2013/03/17/category-theory-reveals-value-of-autoiconicity/"/>
    <updated>2013-03-17T08:06:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://rebcabin.github.com/blog/2013/03/17/category-theory-reveals-value-of-autoiconicity</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Suddenly it hit me: Category Theory is to Math as Lisp is to Programming. I’ve always had an instinctive preference for autoiconic programming languages over non-autoiconic, and now I know why.</p>

<p>An autoiconic language is one in which the format for code and the
format for data are identical. Add “quote” and you have instant
metaprogramming built-in. That means that when you write code, you’re
really writing a DSL (Domain-Specific Language), <em>always</em>. With
non-autoiconic languages, e.g., all the C’s, Javas, Algols and
Fortrans, that is, the mainstream, DSLs are a special case and
require tons of enabling machinery like expression-object-models,
serializers, lexers, yaccers, compilers, decompilers, metadata
managers, and on and on. All standard or near standard, and all
equally unnecessary since none of it at bottom does any more nor less
than quote, quasi-quote, and unquote.</p>

<p>With Haskell and its ancestors Miranda, KRC, and SASL; and with Scala,
F#, and all the ML’s, DSL programming is done via user-defined types.
With these languages, DSL programming is not a special case, but
remoting <em>is</em> still a special case requiring extra machinery. This is
not a small thing, but really the crux of the argument. The real gold
in the era of cloud programmability is DSL + remoting. I need to send
expressions written in my DSLs to servers – for data affinity, and to
clients – for data privacy.</p>

<p>Granted one might say “the difference is just a matter of degree.”
True, but that’s like saying the difference between a rock and the
entire Earth is just a matter of degree. That’s why the Lisps won’t
die: it’s just plain <em>easier</em> to write remotable DSLs in Lisp, by
<em>orders of magnitude</em>, and you <em>always</em> need remotable DSLs. And
remotable DSLs are enabled by distributed metaprogramming platforms.</p>

<p>I argue that any sufficiently rich application will become a
distributed metaprogramming platform eventually, and will need all
that stuff. Especially on the web, where code-remoting is a necessity
– confer the massive amounts of machinery and years of work behind
.NET Expressions for <code>IQueryable</code> and friends. Beautiful,
it’s true, because the thinking and the engineering behind them were
first-rate and I was privileged to participate. But, if our mainstream
languages had been Mathematica or some kinds of Lisp, remoting and
rewriting would have been for-free; a “duh, obviously;” not even an
afterthought; but a built-in assumption. Reflecting on the whole
DSL-enabling infrastructure of .NET Expressions, they’re nothing but
an implementation of quote, quasi-quote, and unquote for C#. All that
work just to get <em>into</em> the mineshaft where the gold of remotable DSLs
lies.</p>

<p>This entire screed is just an addendum to
<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Greenspun's_tenth_rule">Greenspun’s Tenth Rule</a>,
my asserting that the <em>specific</em> thing that these “sufficiently
complicated C or Fortran” programs strive to find in their “ad-hoc,
informally specified, bug-ridden, slow implementations of half of
Common Lisp” – the specific half they need – is the half that
enables DSLs, namely distributed, remotable metaprogramming via quote,
quasi-quote, and unquote.</p>

<!--
That means you write code that rewrites code without excess machinery. That means that all of DSLs (Domain-Specific Languages), code remoting for affinity and privacy, optimizers, query planners, all the stuff that any sophisticated application eventually needs, are enabled out-of-the-box. With non-autoiconic languages, you have to write tons and tons and tons of machinery to get that done: reflection, object models for expressions, serializers, metadata managers, lexers, yaccers, compilers, decompilers. All standard or near standard, and equally unnecessary, because all of it does nothing more nor less than quote, quasi-quote, and unquote. 
-->

<p>What does this have to do with Category Theory? That is a use of
autoiconicity in mathematics. It uses the language of mathematics to
explain mathematics. Every branch of mathematics is just a DSL of
Category Theory.</p>

<p>All this philosophizing came about because <a href="http://blog.fogus.me/2012/07/09/clojure-obscura/">Fogus, of “Joy of Clojure”</a> recently tweeted about <a href="http://mitpress.mit.edu/sicp/">SICP – Structure and Interpretation of Computer Programs</a>, which is now influencing its second or third generation of developers. That reminded me of <a href="http://www.cs.kent.ac.uk/people/staff/dat/miranda/wadler87.pdf">Philip Wadler’s critique of SICP</a> and got me thinking why I always thought that, outside of his pedagogical context, Wadler’s argument was weak. Then I remembered that <a href="http://www.johndcook.com/blog/">John D. Cook, of “The Endeavor”</a> sent around a link to a <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1302.6946.pdf">deeply intriguing new book by David I. Spivak on category theory</a>, and it hit me.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
